

Artist Bio & Curriculum Vitae

Artist Bio

Amay Kataria (b. New Delhi, India) is a graduate from the School of the Art Institute of Chicago (2019) with an MFA in Art & Technology Studies. After completing his bachelors in Computer Engineering from Virginia Tech (2012), he worked for Microsoft Corp. (2013-2017) in Seattle, WA. He has been invited as a visiting artist at the Ethereal Summit, ThoughtWorks and Bellas Artes Outpost and was awarded the New Media Art Residency at Art Center Nabi. He has participated in group shows at the Art Institute of Chicago, USA (2017), Experimental Sound Studio, Chicago, USA (2018), Sullivan Galleries, Chicago, USA (2018), Art Center Nabi, Seoul, South Korea (2018), ThoughtWorks, New York, USA (2018) and Bajaj Bhawan, Mumbai, India (2019). To support his work, he has received grants in the name of Shapiro Level-Up Research Grant and Bajaj Art Scholarship.

Amay Kataria

<u>akataria@saic.edu</u> - <u>www.amaykataria.com</u> - <u>www.github.com/eulphean</u>

Education

MFA, Art & Technology Studies, May 2019

School of the Art Institute of Chicago

Concentration in developing a transdisciplinary, research based art practice to interrogate concepts with new media.

Awards Bajaj Art Scholarship (2019), Shapiro Research Level-Up Grant (2018)

B.S., Computer Engineering, December 2012

Virginia Tech

Concentration in embedded systems, hardware-software design, data structures & algorithms, and interdisciplinary product design.

CGPA 3.84, Rank 6/126 Summa Cum Laude

Awards Bernard Silverman, Byron M. & Helen S. Brumback, Gilbert & Lucille Seay, MR. & CP. Staley Memorial, Litton Industries, Benjamin F.Bock, James Milton Beattie Jr.

Skills & Tools

Code C++, Javascript, Python, Java, C#, Solidity, Objective-C, Swift, C

Libraries OpenFrameworks, P5.js, Processing, React/React-Native, AngularJS, EmberJS, Bootstrap

Sensor Boards Arduino, Teensy, Beaglebone, Raspberry Pi, Asus Tinker Board

Kinetics DC/Servo/Stepper motors, Motor Controller, Mechanisms

3D Rhino, Grasshopper, Blender, Unity, 3D printing, Photogrammetry, HoloLens

Sound Audio Digital Signal Processing (DSP), Ableton Live, PureData, MaxMSP

Design Sketch, GIMP, Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Illustrator, Adobe After-Effects

Work Experience

Teaching Assistant, School of the Art Institute of Chicago, 2017 - 2018
Interactive Art & Intro to Computer Vision and Machine Learning with *Christopher Baker*Kinetics and Computer Control with *Jacob Tonski*Digital Light Projection with *Jan Tichy*

Lab Assistant, School of the Art Institute of Chicago, 2017 - 2018 Electronics and Kinetics Lab

Creative Technologist, School of the Art Institute of Chicago, May - July, 2018 Expanded and engineered new Light Kits for Jan Tichy's Digital Light Projection class. This included PCB design and programming a new Arduino library with examples to guide first-time students through digital light production.

Software Engineer II, Microsoft Corp., May 2013 - June 2017 Skype for Consumers, Skype for Business, Window Hyper-V Seattle, WA

Software Engineering Intern, Qualcomm, May 2012 - August 2012, San Diego, California

Systems Solutions Engineering Intern, Harris Corporation, January - August, 2010 Lynchburg, Virginia

Residencies & Workshops

Visiting Artist, Bellas Artes Projects, Manilla, Philippines, June 2019 A two-day workshop on Context-Responsive Art Practice with Raqs Media Collective as part of Eskwela, an experimental school for transdisciplinary thought process and art making.

New Media Artist in Resident, Art Center Nabi, Seoul, Korea, July-September 2018.

Visiting Artist, Ethereal Summit, New York City, May 2018
Art & Blockchain conference in New York as part of the maker-space hosted by New York-based artist, Jessica Angel.

Art-A-Hack Resident, ThoughtWorks, New York City, June-July 2018

Creative Commissions

Encryption Archive, New work commission for Dylan Fish Boundless Encounters HangZhou Triennial of Fiber Art, China, November 2019

Ethereum Farm, New work commission for Stephanie Rothenberg ReThinking Labor Sullivan Galleries, Chicago, USA, September 2019

Frayed Continuum, Arduino code to drive motors for Ayesha Singh It Was Never Concrete
Shrine Empire, New Delhi, India, August 2019

Long Memory, Arduino code to drive hacked hard drives for Ziv Z'eev Cohen Remanence/Remnants
062 Gallery, Zhoub Art Center, Chicago, USA, August 2019

RGBY, Arduino & Raspberry Pi code to drive Neon for Yaazd Hafeez Contractor NYCxDesign
New York City, USA, May 2019

Small-Pop Hypothesis, Electronics & Arduino code for Galen Odell-Smedley MFA Thesis Show 2018
Sullivan Galleries, Chicago, USA, May 2018

Exhibition History

2019

Babble Wall & Figments of Attention

Future is Here: Art & Technology in a Millenial Age curated by Dr. Arshiya Lokhandwala Phoenix City Mall, Chennai, India November 8, 2019

The Nest

Error: The Art of Imperfection curated by John Duncan Bass Ars Electronica, Linz, Austria September 5, 2019 Figments of Desire
MFA Thesis Show curated by Rohan Ayinde Smith
Sullivan Galleries, Chicago, USA
April - June, 2019

Speculative Bitcoin Wallet & Groove Body Student display case curated by Anna Yu Art Institute of Chicago, USA March - April, 2019

Babble Wall & Figments of Attention Future is Here: Art & Technology in a Millenial Age curated by Dr. Arshiya Lokhandwala Bajaj Bhawan, Mumbai, India January - April, 2019

2018

Groove Body
Nabi Artist Residency 2018 Exhibition
Art Center Nabi, Seoul, South Korea
September - November, 2018

2° Window Art-A-Hack Exhibition Thoughtworks, New York City, USA July, 2018

Ontology of Cryptocollectibles
Art & Blockchain Hack Space
Ethereal Summit, New York City, USA
May, 2018

Bad Breath Waveforms Experimental Sound Studio, Chicago, USA April, 2018

Generative Decay
Algomotion
Art Institute of Chicago, USA
May - August, 2018

2017

Parabolic Dish
Creative Coding Exhibition
Art Institute of Chicago, USA
December, 2018 - February, 2018

Tree of Life
Interactive Performance
Art Institute of Chicago, USA
December, 2017

#40, #60 Answering Machine Art Institute of Chicago, USA October, 2017

Publication & Press

School of the Art Institute of Chicago, Art & Technology Studies Brochure, *Groove Body*, August 2019

School of the Art Institute of Chicago, Grad View Book, Small-Pop Hypothesis (Galen Odell-Smedley & Amay Kataria), January 2019

The Times of India, With New-Age Tech, Millennials Shape Art For The Future, January 17, 2019

Indian Express, Reality Bytes, January 25, 2019

Vogue, How Is Technology Affecting Millennials?, January 17, 2019

Gwangju Ilbo, Dreaming Of A City Of Media Art In Gwangju, October 9, 2018

Coindesk Korea, What's Up, Blockchain?, October 16, 2018

Coindesk Korea, *My Face Is 'Chained' To The Ethereum Blockchain*, September 28, 2018

Blockinpress, *Paying For Art With My Mugshot? Blockchain Meets Art*, September 21, 2018

Crown Goose Blog, 'Nabi Artist Residency 2018' Intersection Of Art and Technology, September 14, 2018

CoinNews, Blockchain Art, September 5, 2018

Blockinpress, When Blockchain Meets Art; Amay Katria and Matthias Dörfelt, August 20, 2018

Public Talks

Autopoiesis, Artist Talk, Art & Technology Studies, SAIC, March 2019

Art x Body x Blockchain, Artist Talk, Art Center Nabi, Seoul, South Korea, August 2018

Github Workshop, Art & Technology Studies, SAIC, November 2017